<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<html>
<head>
  <meta title="M3 Pagination Demo" author="pdfml" />
  <style>
    page { size: A4; margin: 20mm; }
    body { font-family: "Liberation Sans"; font-size: 10pt; color: #333; line-height: 1.4; }

    h1 { font-size: 22pt; color: #1a1a2e; margin-bottom: 12pt; }
    h2 { font-size: 16pt; color: #16213e; margin-top: 20pt; margin-bottom: 10pt; page-break-after: avoid; }
    h3 { font-size: 13pt; color: #0f3460; margin-top: 14pt; margin-bottom: 8pt; }

    p { margin-bottom: 8pt; orphans: 3; widows: 3; }

    .highlight-box {
      background-color: #f0f4ff;
      border: 1pt solid #3366cc;
      padding: 12pt;
      margin-bottom: 12pt;
      page-break-inside: avoid;
    }

    .card {
      background-color: #fafafa;
      border: 0.5pt solid #ddd;
      padding: 10pt;
      margin-bottom: 10pt;
      page-break-inside: avoid;
    }

    table { width: 100%; border-collapse: collapse; margin-top: 10pt; margin-bottom: 10pt; }
    th { font-weight: bold; background-color: #1a1a2e; color: white; padding: 8pt 6pt; text-align: left; }
    td { border-bottom: 0.5pt solid #ddd; padding: 6pt; }
    tr.alt { background-color: #f8f8f8; }

    .section-break { page-break-before: always; }

    first-header {
      border-bottom: 2pt solid #1a1a2e;
      padding-bottom: 8pt;
      margin-bottom: 12pt;
    }
    page-header {
      border-bottom: 1pt solid #ccc;
      padding-bottom: 4pt;
      margin-bottom: 8pt;
      font-size: 8pt;
      color: #999;
    }
    page-footer {
      text-align: center;
      font-size: 8pt;
      color: #999;
      border-top: 0.5pt solid #ddd;
      padding-top: 4pt;
    }
  </style>
</head>
<body>
  <!-- First-page header (appears ONLY on page 1) -->
  <first-header>
    <h1>PDFML — M3 Pagination Demo</h1>
    <p><em>This document demonstrates CSS page-break control, orphans/widows, and differentiated first-page headers.</em></p>
  </first-header>

  <!-- Standard header (appears on pages 2, 3, ...) -->
  <header>
    <p>PDFML Pagination Demo — Continued</p>
  </header>

  <footer>
    <p>Page <page-number/> of <page-count/> — Generated by pdfml</p>
  </footer>

  <main>
    <!-- SECTION 1: page-break-inside: avoid -->
    <h2>1. page-break-inside: avoid</h2>
    <p>The boxes below have <code>page-break-inside: avoid</code> applied. Instead of being split across pages, each box will be moved entirely to the next page if it doesn't fit.</p>

    <div class="highlight-box">
      <h3>Feature Card A</h3>
      <p>This entire card is kept together on one page. The layout engine checks if the box fits in the remaining space. If it doesn't, the box is moved to a fresh page rather than being split.</p>
      <p>This prevents ugly breaks in the middle of visually grouped content like cards, alerts, or callout boxes.</p>
    </div>

    <div class="highlight-box">
      <h3>Feature Card B</h3>
      <p>Another avoid-break box. Notice how no card is ever cut in half across a page boundary. This is critical for professional document output.</p>
      <p>Without this feature, a box's top half might appear at the bottom of one page and the bottom half at the top of the next — something that looks terrible in printed documents.</p>
    </div>

    <p>Here is some filler text to push content down the page and demonstrate page breaks happening naturally between elements.</p>
    <p>The layout engine intelligently decides where to break. It respects the CSS cascade, meaning you can set page-break-inside: avoid on specific classes without affecting the rest of the document.</p>
    <p>This is paragraph three of additional content. We need enough text to push the layout across the page boundary so the next section demonstrates forced breaks.</p>
    <p>Additional paragraph to extend the content area. The pagination engine processes each direct child of the body element sequentially, checking overflow conditions at every step.</p>
    <p>More content to fill the page. This is important because we want to see how the engine handles the transition from page 1 to page 2, especially with the differentiated headers.</p>
    <p>Notice that page 1 has the large title header, while page 2 shows the smaller continuation header. This is the first-header/first-footer feature in action.</p>

    <div class="card">
      <h3>Compact Card 1</h3>
      <p>This card uses page-break-inside: avoid. If it can't fit at the bottom of the current page, it moves entirely to the next one.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="card">
      <h3>Compact Card 2</h3>
      <p>Another card that stays together. This demonstrates the feature working with multiple consecutive avoid-break elements.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="card">
      <h3>Compact Card 3</h3>
      <p>Third card in the sequence. Each one independently checks whether it fits on the current page.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="card">
      <h3>Compact Card 4</h3>
      <p>Fourth card. At this point, we should be seeing cards flowing across pages while maintaining their integrity.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="card">
      <h3>Compact Card 5</h3>
      <p>Fifth and final card in this demonstration section. The pagination algorithm handles each one cleanly.</p>
    </div>

    <!-- SECTION 2: page-break-before: always (FORCED) -->
    <div class="section-break">
      <h2>2. page-break-before: always</h2>
      <p>This section has <code>page-break-before: always</code> applied via CSS. Regardless of how much space remains on the previous page, this section starts on a fresh page.</p>
      <p>This is essential for documents like legal contracts, where each section must begin on its own page, or reports where chapters need clear separation.</p>
    </div>

    <!-- SECTION 3: Long table to demonstrate pagination -->
    <div class="section-break">
      <h2>3. Multi-Page Data Table</h2>
      <p>The table below contains many rows to demonstrate how tables flow across pages. Notice the clean page transitions.</p>

      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr><th>ID</th><th>Product</th><th>Category</th><th>Price</th><th>Status</th></tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr><td>001</td><td>Cloud Server (8 vCPU)</td><td>Infrastructure</td><td>$299/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>002</td><td>Load Balancer</td><td>Networking</td><td>$49/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr><td>003</td><td>Managed Database</td><td>Data</td><td>$199/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>004</td><td>Object Storage (1TB)</td><td>Storage</td><td>$23/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr><td>005</td><td>CDN (Global)</td><td>Networking</td><td>$89/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>006</td><td>SSL Certificate</td><td>Security</td><td>$12/yr</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr><td>007</td><td>DDoS Protection</td><td>Security</td><td>$149/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>008</td><td>DNS Management</td><td>Networking</td><td>$5/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr><td>009</td><td>Container Registry</td><td>DevOps</td><td>$25/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>010</td><td>CI/CD Pipeline</td><td>DevOps</td><td>$39/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr><td>011</td><td>Monitoring Suite</td><td>Observability</td><td>$79/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>012</td><td>Log Analytics</td><td>Observability</td><td>$45/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr><td>013</td><td>API Gateway</td><td>Integration</td><td>$59/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>014</td><td>Message Queue</td><td>Integration</td><td>$35/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr><td>015</td><td>Serverless Functions</td><td>Compute</td><td>$0.20/1M</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>016</td><td>GPU Instance</td><td>AI/ML</td><td>$899/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr><td>017</td><td>Data Warehouse</td><td>Analytics</td><td>$349/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>018</td><td>Email Service</td><td>Communication</td><td>$15/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr><td>019</td><td>Push Notifications</td><td>Communication</td><td>$29/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
          <tr class="alt"><td>020</td><td>Identity Management</td><td>Security</td><td>$99/mo</td><td>Active</td></tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </div>

    <!-- SECTION 4: Orphans/Widows demo -->
    <div class="section-break">
      <h2>4. Orphans and Widows</h2>
      <p>The paragraphs in this document use <code>orphans: 3; widows: 3;</code> which means the layout engine ensures at least 3 lines appear at the bottom of a page before a break, and at least 3 lines appear at the top of the next page after a break.</p>
      <p>This prevents the common typographical error of having a single lonely line stranded at the top or bottom of a page, which looks unprofessional in printed documents.</p>
      <p>Professional typesetting has enforced orphan and widow rules for centuries. The term "orphan" refers to the first line of a paragraph stranded alone at the bottom of a page, while "widow" refers to the last line stranded at the top of the next page. Both are considered bad practice in professional publishing.</p>
      <p>By setting these CSS properties, you get automatic protection against these typographical issues without having to manually adjust your content. The layout engine handles it during pagination.</p>
      <p>This is the final section of the M3 pagination demo. Thank you for exploring the advanced pagination features of pdfml!</p>
    </div>
  </main>
</body>
</html>
